Dover, N.H. First Parish Church records, 1614-1862.
Congregational Library Archives
Dover, N.H. First Parish Church records, 1614-1862.
1614 1967
1614-1862, 1967
RG1319
Congregational Library Archives
.83 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes, 2 reels)
Gathered in 1633, the First Parish Church in Dover is the oldest church in New Hampshire. Rev. Hanserd Knollys organized the First Parish Church as a religious organization in 1638. The church joined the United Church of Christ in 1961 and the name changed to First Parish Congregational Church in 1996. Records include births, marriages, deaths, dismissals, disciplinary cases, meeting minutes, financial records, and pew plans; letters by Rev. Jeremy Belknap, Rev. Hubbard Winslow, and the church's clerk Asa A. Tufts, and between congregations.
Belknap, Jeremy, 1744-1798
First Parish Church (Dover, N.H.)
Tufts, Asa Alford, 1798-1884
Winslow, Hubbard, 1799-1864
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were received at two different dates. Microform materials (RG1319) were received at an unknown date. The remaining materials (originally RG5360) were loaned to the Congregational Library & Archives from the First Parish Congregational Church (Dover, N.H.); Accession 2017-17.
Location of Originals
The physical materials in this collection are held by the First Parish Church in Dover, New Hampshire. The Congregational Library & Archives maintains digital and microfilm surrogates for much of the colection.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected for this collection in the form of full-text transcription. There is no anticipated date for this accrual.
Custodial History
Microfilm copies were created by the Genealogical Society, Salt Lake City, Utah, in 1967.
Historical note
Gathered in 1633, the First Parish Church in Dover is the oldest church in New Hampshire. The first permanent settlement in New Hampshire, the lands that would eventually become Dover were initially settled by a pair of fishmongers from London. In 1633, the land was bought by a group of English Puritans. Over the next 150 years, with the arrival of mills and other infrastructure, the small settlement grew in population, size and prosperity.
The settlement's first church services were held on the last Sunday of October 1633 by Rev. Leverich at Dover Point; a year later the first meeting house was built on the same location. Little is known about the first meeting house except that it was made of mud and logs with a thatched roof and that it served the community's purposes until 1658 when a new meeting house was erected on Dover Neck. The third meeting house was located on Pine Hill from 1710-1759. In 1758 the fourth meeting house, built out of wood, was constructed in Tuttle Square. Construction on the fifth, and final, meeting house, a new brick church building, was concluded with its dedication on December 31, 1829.
Rev. William Leverich was the first minister to hold church services in Dover in 1633 and is considered the founder of Mission and Action in Dover. Rev. Hanserd Knollys organized the First Parish Church as a religious organization in 1638. Rev. Jeremy Belknap, who wrote the three volume "History of New Hampshire" and founded the Massachusetts Historical Society in 1791, was the minister at the First Parish from 1769-1786. Rev. David Root was well-known for his opposition to slavery and his anti-slavery sermons, as was his successor Rev. Jeremiah S. Young, who on October 28, 1841 passed a resolution against slavery.
The First Parish Church joined the United Church of Christ in 1961 and in 1996 the name changed to First Parish Congregational Church in 1996. It is a member of the New Hampshire Conference, UCC and of the Carroll-Strafford Association. The First Parish Congregational Church continues to serve the community of Dover, New Hampshire, today.
Ministers
William Leverich 1633-1635
George Burdet 1637-1638
Hanserd Knollys 1638-1640
Thomas Larkham 1640-1642
Daniel Maud 1642-1655
John Reyner 1655-1669
John Reyner, Jr. 1669-1676
John Pike 1678-1710
Nicholas Sever 1711-1715
Jonathan Cushing 1717-1769
Jeremy Belknap 1769-1786
Robert Gray 1787-1805
Caleb H. Shearman 1807-1812
Joseph W. Clary 1812-1828
Hubbard Winslow 1828-1831
David Root 1833-1839
Jeremiah S. Young 1839-1843
Homer Barrows 1845-1852
Benjamin F. Parsons 1853-1856
Elias H. Richardson 1856-1863
Avery S. Walker 1864-1868
George B. Spalding 1869-1883
George E. Hall 1884-1908
Evarts W. Pond 1909-1912
Walter A. Morgan 1913-1917
Robert W. Coe 1918-1921
Lewis E. Purdum 1921-1929
David P. Hatch 1929-1938
Ralph S. Huffer 1939-1965
William W. Tucker 1965-1971
L. Arthur Domingue 1972-1978
William U. Conway 1978-1986
J. E. Lane 1985-1987
David L. Slater 1988-2009
R. E. Staley 1988-1992
J. G. Pirie 1993-1994
R. L. Hirtle 1993-1994
G. L. Crouch, Jr. 1994-1998
K. Geuther 1998-2004
J. G. Pirie 2000-2001
A. Campbell 2001-2004
N. M. Talbott 2004-2009
J. Mcardle 2009-2010
N. B. Bendroth 2009-2010
J. W. Lynes 2011-2012
M. S. Bennet 2012-2017
Scope and Contents
The Dover, N.H. First Parish Church records consist of administrative church records and correspondence from 1614-1862. The scope includes records of births, marriages, deaths, meeting minutes, financial records, and pew plans; letters by appointed clergymen, including Jeremy Belknap, Hubbard Winslow, and Asa A. Tufts, between congregations, and from parishioners wishing to leave the congregation. Microfilm materials duplicate some of the physical material but additional correspondence not present in the physical material are present on the microfilm.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three series. Records in each series have been arranged chronologically, by start date, and by topic.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1639-1855
Series 2: Church Records, 1717-1857
Series 3: Microfilm, 1614-1862
Technical Requirements
A microfilm reader is required in order to access microform materials. One microfilm reader is available to the public upon request.
To access digital user's copies via online-interface, a java-enabled web browser is required. Internet Explorer 8.x and later, Firefox 5.x and later, Opera 12 and later, Safari 5.x and later, or any version of Google Chrome are recommended.
Bibliography
Bryant, Donald R. History of the First Parish Church Founded 1633. Dover: First Parish Church, 2002.
Antislavery movements.; Baptismal records.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Congregational churches.; Installation (clergy).; Marriage records.; New England's Hidden Histories.; Pews and pew rights.; Belknap, Jeremy, 1744-1798; First Parish Church (Dover, N.H.)
- Correspondence, 1639 1855; 1639-1855; 11 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence contains letters by appointed clergymen, including Jeremy Belknap, Hubbard Winslow, David Root, Asa A. Tufts, Homer Barrows, and Jeremiah Young. There are correspondences between congregations and letters written on paper with the anti-slavery letterhead from parishioners wishing to leave the congregation.
  - Letter of public assurance, 1639
    Digital Copies
    This document was digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    This single-page document consists of a "letter of public assurance" addressed "to all public officers and others in this jurisdiction whom this may concern". The content relates to the case of Separatist minister "Mr. Hansard Knollys" (Rev. Hanserd Knollys, 1599–1691) who was subject to prosecution on charges brought against him by the high commission court in England. In the letter, the unsigned authors grant legal assurance of safe passage for Rev. Knollys during his trial.
  - Belknap, 1786
    These church records were digitized as part of the New England's Hidden Histories project. Digital reproductions are available to view online.
    These six items of correspondence were all authored by the Rev. Jeremy Belknap, a Congregational minister better known for his contributions to the corpus of American historical works. After twenty years as minister to the Parish Church in Dover, Rev. Belknap resigned due to the church's failure to resolve his salary complaints. The letters ennumerated below correspond to this dispute, which reached a breaking point in the spring and summer of 1786 and resulted in Rev. Belknap's dissolution of his ministry.
    Item list
    1786 April 30
    from Rev. Belknap to the First Parish in Dover: letter regarding Rev. Belknap's effort to lobby for an increase in salary due to the depreciation of paper currency
    1786 June 12
    from Rev. Belknap to the First Parish in Dover: letter declining the church committee's invitation to converse about the current "difficulties"
    1786 June 15
    from Rev. Belknap to the First Parish in Dover: letter confirming Rev. Belknap's decision to resign from his former duties
    1786 June 16
    from Rev. Belknap to the First Parish in Dover: letter with a further reiteration of Rev. Belknap's intentions
    from Rev. Belknap to the First Parish in Dover: letter with request for an official dismissal or alternatively the convening of an Ecclesiastical Council to decide the matter
    1786 July 27
    from Rev. Belknap to the First Parish in Dover: typewritten copy of an original letter elaborating on the reasons for Rev. Belknap's resignation, including objection to the practice of a general parish tax as a means to pay his salary
  - Correspondence, 1828 1838; 1828-1838
    These official church records deal mainly with ministerial business, including invitations to clergy to preach and their responses. There is also a parishioner recommendation letter and a copy of meeting minutes. Items are ennumerated below.
    1828 September 13
    by Asa Tufts [secretary]: meeting minutes
    1828 November 23
    from Hubbard Windlay to the Church and Society of the First Congregational Parish of Dover: letter declining invitation to preach regularly
    1831 November 30
    from J. H. Keeler to Asa Tufts: letter excusing himself from an ecclesiastical council
    1831 December 7
    from "L" to [unknown]: letter requesting references for two potential ministers
    1832 May 28
    from A. D. Eddy to William Woodman: letter with description of recent travels
    1832 October 23
    from Warren Fay to the First Church in Dover: letter declining ministerial call
    1838 August 6
    from the Congregational Church in Great Falls to the First Church in Dover: letter of recommendation for parishioner Oliver Carter
  - Winslow, 1831
    These records relate to the ministry of Rev. H. Winslow, specifically the end of his ministry, his health concerns, and the search for a replacement minister.
    1831 June 11
    from Rev. H. Winslow to "the wardens of the First Parish in Dover": letter describing his health concerns and need for a new pastor
    from Rev. H. Winslow to "the wardens of the First Parish in Dover": copy of above letter with reply from church wardens
    1831 November 13
    from Rev. H. Winslow to Dr. Asa A. Tufts: letter describing his health concerns
    by Israel W. Putnam [moderator]: results of an ecclesiastical council dismissing Rev. Winslow
    1831 December 11
    from H. Winslow to Dr. Asa A. Tufts: letter suggesting replacement ministers
  - Backus, 1831 1835; 1831-1835
    These records relate to the church's attempt to instate Rev. J. Turnbull Backus as minister, and Backus's refusals of the call. One letter includes arrangements for temporary preaching.
    1831 August 19
    from Allen Gannett to William Woodman: recommendation of J. T. Backus as replacement minister
    1832 February 13
    from J. Turnbull Backus to William Woodman: letter declining the ministerial call
    1831 October 31
    from J. Turnbull Backus to William Woodman: letter reiterating his poor health and declining the ministerial call
    1831 August 24
    from J. Turnbull Backus to William Woodman: letter with arrangements for preaching
  - Root, 1833 1839; 1833-1839
    These records, mainly correspondence, relate to the ministry of Rev. David Root, specifically to his illness and resignation. They include letters from Rev. Root to the church committee and replies.
    undated
    from Rev. David Root to the First Parish in Dover: copy of letter declining preaching due to ill health
    1833 January 21
    from Rev. David Root to the committee of the First Church and Parish in Dover: letter regarding his ministry
    1834 April 24
    from Charles Ricker to Rev. David Root: letter regarding his dismission
    1835 March 25
    from J. H. Miller to the First Church in Dover: invitation to an ecclesiastical council for the merging of the Pleasant Street Church in Portsmouth, N.H. and the North Church
    1835 May 28
    from Rev. David Root to the First Parish of Dover: copy of resignation letter
    1837 June 10
    from Rev. David Root to the First Congregational Church of Dover: letter calling for an ecclesiastical council regarding his resignation
  - Norris, 1834 1839; 1834-1839
    These records relate to the disciplinary case of parishioner Daniel Norris, resulting from a financial dispute with other parishioners. Documents include legal testimonials by witnesses and plaintifs in the case, summons to the hearing, and finally Norris's confession to the church. Items are ennumerated below.
    1834 February 10
    by T. E. Sawyer: copy of receipt by Richard McDuffee to Thomas Roberts, with elaboration of legal dispute
    1835 March 17
    from John W. Hayes to Daniel Norris [on behalf of the church]: letter with summons to a disciplinary hearing
    1835 March 23
    by Thomas Roberts: legal testimony
    1835 March 26
    by John W. Hayes: report on disciplinary case of Daniel Norris
    1835 January 19
    by Thomas Pickering, David Legro, and Richard McDuffee: legal testimony
    1839 February 5
    from Daniel Norris to the congregation of the First Church in Dover: confession and request for forgiveness
  - Correspondence, 1839 1842; 1839-1842
    These records comprise letters to and from the church in Dover, discussing pulpit supply and preaching, disciplinary cases of parishioners, and one request for dismissal. Items are ennumerated below.
    1839 August 28
    from E. J. Lane to Rev. Mr. Young: letter with request for pulpit supply
    1839 September 4
    from William J. Breed to E. J. Lane: letter making arrangements for preaching
    1839 October 10
    from Rev. J. S. Young to the committee of the First Church in Dover: letter declining offer to continue preaching
    1842 July 6
    from Rev. J. S. Young to Charles Ricker: letter with summons to a disciplinary hearing
    1842 July 8
    from E. J. Lane to Mr. Palfrey Downing: letter with summons to a disciplinary meeting
    1842 July 10
    from Elizabeth L. Fols to the Congregational Church in Dover: letter asking for dismissal
  - A. Folsom and Others, 1842
    These records relate to the departure of several parishioners from the church in Dover, and the church's subsequent dismissal of the members. In a document submitted to the church, the absenting members describe their opposition to the church's refusal to condemn slavery.
    1842 October 9
    from Abraham Folsom to the First Congregational Church in Dover: letter regarding the abolition of slavery
    by the First Church in Dover: letter dismissing Abraham Folsom and other members
  - Correspondence, 1845 1849; 1845-1849
    These records consist of official church correspondence, including parishioner transfer letters, ministers' letters, invitations to ecclesiastical councils, and summons to disciplinary meetings. Items are ennumerated below.
    1845 June 14
    from Homer Barrow to the First Congregational Church and Society in Dover: letter with acceptance of ministerial call
    1845 June 23
    from the First Congregational Church of Christ in Dover to the Congregational Church of Christ in Rochester: invitation to ecclesiastical council for the ordination of Rev. Homer Barrow
    1848 September 4
    from the First Church in Dover to the First Presbyterian Church in Newburyport: parishioner transfer of Hannah Coffin
    from the First Church in Dover to the Baptist Church in Dover: parishioner transfer of "Miss A. B."
    from the First Church in Dover to Daniel Gale: letter with summons to a disciplinary hearing
    from the First Church in Dover to Samuel Prescott: letter with summons to a disciplinary hearing
    1849 March 1
    from Hayden K. Higby to E. J. Lane: letter requesting letter of transfer to the Old South Church in Boston
  - Congregations, 1853 1855; 1853-1855
    These records comprise four invitations to ecclesiastical councils, from other churches to the church in Dover. The invitations are for ordinations and dismissions of ministers.
    1853 December 22
    from the Congregational Church in Great Falls to the Congregational Church in Dover: invitation to ecclesiastical council for dismission of Rev. McCollom
    1853 December 12
    from the Congregational Church in Epping to the Congregational Church in Dover: invitation to ecclesiastical council for the ordination of Rev. Lyman White
    1855 October 31
    from the Congregational Church in Hampton to the Congregational Church in Dover: invitation to ecclesiastical council for the ordination of Rev. John Colby
    1855 October 22
    from the North Church and Parish in Portsmouth, N.H. to the Congregational Church in Dover: invitation to ecclesiastical council for the ordination of Rev. Lyman Whiting
- Church records, 1717 1857; 1717-1857; 9 Items; (5 folder, 4 volumes)
  Church Records include records of births, marriages, deaths, meeting minutes and financial outlines of the pews. There are documents regarding the instalment of Rev. Benjamin F. Parsons, lists of congregation members, documents regarding the situation of A. Farnsworth, and tax documents.
  - Church record of marriages, baptisms and deaths, 1717 1829; 1717-1829
    The Church Record of Marriages, Baptisms, and Deaths is a volume containing records of Marriages: May 1767 - Jan. 1829; and Baptisms and deaths: Oct. 1717 - Dec. 1786. It is signed by Jeremy Belknap.
  - Church record book, 1762 1862; 1762-1862
    This record book consists of committee reports, meeting minutes, correspondence drafts and copies, as well as financial records.
    Separated Materials
    Between pages 122-123, three loose documents were found in and placed in their own folder: Tax Documents 1781-1784.
  - Church record book vol. 1, 1766 1829; 1766-1829
    The Curch record book vol. 1 contains Jeremy Belknap's historical notes on the town and church of Dover until October 1789. The volume also contains records of marriages and baptisms, lists of members admitted to the church, a list of the childrne of Rev. Jonathan Cushing, and notes written by other clergymen.
  - Church record book vol. 2, 1831 1857; 1831-1857
    The Church record book vol. 2 contains names of church members, records of deaths and baptisms, notices of ministers, and prints of Rev. Hubbard Winslow, Rev. David Root, and Hanserd Knollys There are printed church manual clippings as well as a photograph of Dea. Lane. The title leaf is signed by Asa A. Tufts in 1831.
  - Tax documents, 1781 1784; 1781-1784
    These three loose documents were found in the church record book dating to 1762-1862, between pages 122-123, and placed in their own folder.
    1781 April 10
    by Rev. Jeremy Belknap: notice of receipt for parish taxes levied
    1784 May 1
    by Stephen Evans to the parish wardens: request for payment of one pound, nine shilling and sixpence from the parish collection of 1782
    list of payments received from various subscribers
  - Church records, 1825 1834; 1825-1834
    These records comprise official church correspondence and include invitations to ecclesiastical councils, ordinations, articles of faith and church covenant documents.
    [used by] Rev. Clary: articles of faith
    1828 August 6
    by Jonathan French [moderator]: result of ecclesiastical council dismissing Rev. Clary
    1831 November 16
    from the Church of Christ at Meredeth Bridge to the Church of Christ at Dover: invitation to ecclesiastical council for ordination
    1832 June 6
    from the Church of Christ in Pleasant Street, Portsmouth to the Church of Christ in Dover invitation to ecclesiastical council for ordination
    1833 February 6
    by John Smith [scribe]: result of ecclesiastical council to install Rev. Root
    1833 January 25
    template letter for ordination invitation
    1834 July 15
    articles of faith and covenant
    1835 September 17
    from the Congregational Church in Rochester to the Church in Dover: invitation to ecclesiastical council to dismiss pastor
  - Documents regarding A. Farnsworth, 1840 1841; 1840-1841
    These four documents relate to a disciplinary case against parishioner Asa Farnsworth, who was allegedly seen going into the bedroom of the widow Mrs. Benn without anyone besides the two of them present.
    1840 December 5
    by Francis Cogswell and others: committee report on Asa Farnsworth's behavior toward the widow Mrs. Benn
    1841 April 9
    from Asa Farnsworth to the Congregational Church of Dover: letter relating to his own disciplinary case
    1841 June 28
    draft of ruling in Asa Farnsworth's disciplinary case
  - Church records, 1845 1855; 1845-1855
    These records consist of official church and parish documents, including several meeting minutes and invitations, and also several financial reports. Items are ennumerated below.
    1845 May 11
    by E. J. Lane [clerk]: church and parish meeting minutes
    1849 December 2
    by E. J. Lane [clerk]: church meeting minutes
    1849 December 5
    by B. R. Allen [moderator]: ecclesiastical council meeting minutes
    1852 July 6
    by Adam Jobey [moderator]: ecclesiastical council meeting minutes
    1852 May 27
    meeting notice
    1853 December 16
    from the Mather Church and Society to the First Church in Dover: invitation to ecclesiastical council for ordination
    1854 March 31
    list of subscribers for the American Sunday School Union
    1855 January 1
    reports of the church treasury committee
  - Documents regarding Rev. Parsons, 1852 1853; 1852-1853
    These documents relate to the selection and ordination of Rev. Benjamin Parsons, including correspondence to and from the First Parish Church in Dover. Items are ennumerated below.
    1852 December 28
    from Benjamin Parsons to the Congregational Church and parish in Dover: letter with acceptance of ministerial call
    1852 December 29
    from Benjamin Parsons to the Congregational Church and parish in Dover: addendum to acceptance of call with salary request
    1852 December 31
    from the Congregational Church in Dover to S. L. Pomroy: invitation letter to the installation of Rev. Parsons
    1853 January 12
    by B. N. Allen [moderator]: results of ecclesiastical council for the settlement of Rev. Parsons
- Microfilm, 1614-1862; 1967
  The microfilms contain death, marriage, and baptismal records, calendar notes, and meeting minutes. Also containing letters from Jeremy Belknap and other documents, these microfilms contain much of the material from Series 1 and 2.
  - Dover, NH, First Parish Church records, 1614 1862; 1614-1862; 1967 (Reel 1)
  - Dover, NH, First Parish Church records, 1614 1862; 1614-1862; 1967 (Reel 2)